what was the first step to not feeling
like
meditating yeah I mean making list
admiration right thinking about all the
cool stuff about her
right so uh Master Shanti in the bodh
aatar he makes a comment you know with a
girl you know what it is it's her eyes
or nose or everything else right but
what is it about meditation that's cool
right I my job is to give you all the
cool things about meditation okay here
we go Master sh
[Music]
says you can spend your
time uh reciting holy
rituals what's that
sound next one it's is
coming uh K means you can do all these
rough spiritual practices you can lock
yourself up in three years at
okay you can do those for a long time
you can spend a lot of your time on them
but if your mind is distracted while
you're doing all these holy practices
even yoga right if your mind is
distracted while you're doing them you
need
they become
meaningless okay you you ruin all your
spiritual practices if you don't have
the ability to keep your mind focused
okay also Yoga Yoga Asma same thing if
you don't have the capacity to keep your
mind focused on what you're doing it
doesn't matter how nice the stuff is
because you won't do it well you'll be
distracted okay who who said
that means the one who understands
the way things are which
is so the first cool thing about
meditation that you're supposed to is
supposed to be a selling point for
meditation is
negative if you meditate if you learn to
meditate you won't be distracted and
ruin all your other cool things got it
the first selling point for meditation
is that you won't ruin all your other
good activities by being
distracted you'll be able to focus even
if all you care about is watching TV
you'll be able to focus on TV okay
uh and if it happens that you want to
engage in some act of kindness Act of
goodness your attention you will be more
focused and you will be more what do you
call it
stable and steady when you try to do
something kind okay there are people you
know who try to do good things for
others and they bail out after three
weeks or you know they never quite get
it done they say look I'll come over and
paint your house for you three years
later there's still cans of paint in the
corner and the second room never got
painted right so if you have meditative
Focus everything you do in your life is
done well and it gets
finished and and you're just focused and
you're St what do you call them strong
stable steady you get things done and
you're able to focus and concentrate and
finish things
okaying if you have that kind of focus
where you can stay with a task
firmly m you will quickly it speeds up
your spiritual progress speeds up
everything about your spiritual life you
speed it up if your mind is focused and
study so for example just being able to
focus on your breath for 15 minutes
straight without a break in the morning
is enough to make you a very good
business person okay that's amazing
Michael Gordon told me that right he he
did what TM
Michael Gordon has done TM he's the
owner of Bumble and bubble just sold it
to Estee La for $50 million okay I
said how did you learn to concentrate
like that he says somebody taught me TM
when I was a hi being back in
1968 and I and I never stopped I'm still
doing it it's like 10 minutes a day and
he just does this little meditation
exercise watching his breath and that
made him a $50 million company you see
that you you learn to concentrate at
focus and keep your mind on something
and then stuff comes faster okay
everything comes faster that's their
mind I'm trying to describe to you the
qualities of the girl right got
it the
drifting if you meditate regularly
properly with the right pre what you
call conditions that we talked about you
can reach the St of Clairvoyance okay
you can read other people's minds you
can tell what's going to happen 3 weeks
from now or 6 years from now or 500
years from now you can see huge patterns
in the world and you can see what's
going to happen in your own life ahead
of time and you can and you can fix it
or you can do cool things you see you
can make Supernatural things happen and
you can read other people's minds and
you you can get a a sense of the future
that makes you extremely successful at
whatever you try to do okay if it's
business you already know next year's
products sometimes it's not completely
conscious okay you're designing the next
generation of computer
chip you have a vision into it be six
months before everybody else has it
because you've been meditating and it's
not like you see the plans for the chip
on your table 6 months no it's not like
that you can call it
inspiration you can call it um Instinct
Instinct the cause of instinct is
meditation okay you can have these
incredible instincts that other people
don't have you can discover patterns in
the what do you
call in the web what do you call
Matrix you see patterns in The Matrix 6
months before or a year before or 10
years before other people okay you are a
visionary and and you're just doing
things way ahead of everybody else
because you're meditating and you're
you're actually picking up on what's
already going to happen got it you're
not discovering new stuff you're picking
up on what's already going to happen
because you're meditating and you've
attain some level of par voyance later
on that will get very cool it will go
hundreds of years down you will see
patterns hundreds of you will be doing
things now because you know a certain
thing will happen 500 years from now
it's cool okay that that's really fun
it's one thing to predict next year's
computer Che it's another thing to know
what's going to be going on for 100
years from now on this planet okay
that's kind of cool right and and to be
able to see other worlds and and meet
beans in other worlds and things like
this
kind I don't know it doesn't work for me
to say these things in a business
seminar they just want to know Bri wants
to know what's going to happen next year
with the with the merger with Liberia
you know but frankly in this context I'm
sort of liberating to this these things
can happen you can have these kind of
things happen and that's so cool uh to
see things 100 years out to see patterns
100 years ahead or stuff like you can do
that and that changes your what do you
call
it your scope of your life you know
you're not just doing things for next
year or next week you're doing things
100 years ahead that will affect
thousands or Millions of people you see
and and if you meditate well you can
John fley calls it that thing like you
he's always talking about this cool
thing I always forget the word he said
normally jet airplanes are only allowed
to fly within they're not allowed to go
less than one mile close to each other
and if you're in a
military aircraft and if you have
special permission you can go
within 12 ft or something of other
aircraft if with training and then he
gets to the Blue Angels and they say
okay we're going to fly what was it 36
in we're going to fly three feet from
another plane that weighs 15
Tons 20 tons and costs 4 $40 million and
closes at a speed of 1,000 knots which
you've got to express in miles per hour
which is what it's actually 800 closing
at 1,000 miles per hour right uh he he
describes in his training the act of of
of of jumping to a whole new level of
performance right so you know it used to
be that it was cool if you got within
ice I what do you call within visual
side of another airplane now you're 3
feet
away uh from another plane and combined
you're going a th000 miles hour you know
what I'm saying is that if you meditate
well it's not just that you get some
sort of special insight into what's
going to happen this Comm unit work you
are working 100 years ahead you are
working 500 years ahead you are taking
actions which will affect planets and
it's cool it's like a it's the
difference between a commercial airliner
and a Blue Angel that it like the whole
difference of scale it changes your
whole scope changes you're not worrying
about next week you're worrying about
500 years from now it's it's cool it's
fun okay all right uh you're supposed to
get start you're supposed to start
wanting the girl
okay door even when you sleep you'll be
in a state of
meditation even when you fall
asleep uh you're not exactly sleeping
anymore okay it's a kind of
meditation it's going be kind of
disturbing and you have to have a
teacher
okay naturally if you medit
it starts to
affect your negative emotions you will
be better able to cope with everything
if you do just a little meditation every
day okay just 15 minutes a day if
nothing more Grand than that you won't
get as upset as you used to get at work
okay and with your family and and that's
worth it okay that investment of 15
minutes is worth it if you do yoga for
half an hour 45 minutes a day 1 hour you
will add 20 years of of of good time to
your life 20 30 years it's worth it
right it's just worth it uh and and
doing meditation 15 minutes a day
changes your whole day your whole day
goes smoother that investment of 15
minutes a day makes everybody in the
office happy and it's worth it the time
that you lose people are always worrying
about I'm going to lose 15 minutes in
the morning but you're going to pick up
an office that or your workplace is
going to be pleasant for like 5 hours
isn't that a good trade okay like
[Music]
that he says more
importantly all of the steps to
Liberation right all of the steps to the
point where you become an enlightened
being they will be a cinch if you learn
to meditate okay that's why we're going
to the back of the book first right
because our task for the next 10 years
is to train ourselves in in like 20
spiritual Arts 20 different spiritual
Arts which are graded which are in a
certain order and if you go through them
at the end of the process you are a
being who can help this entire planet
you've got the 500 years ahead Vision
you see you can help people on that
level
uh the real reason to learn to meditate
is that it will help you achieve those
steps don't it the so the rest of the
stuff I said it was
just what do you call trinkets what do
you call costume jewelry okay I mean it
was just little thought seeing the
seeing that what's going to happen on
the planet for the next 500 years is
nothing comp compared to the fact that
if you learn to meditate well then as
you go through these
spiritual practices Arts you will Master
them like that got it meditation will
become your tool to mastering a hundred
other spiritual Arts right and that's
cool it's a tool that you cannot do
without what's s
know you cannot do without it it's a
tool that you're going to have to apply
the rest of your life whether you're
fixing cars or you're getting
enlightened okay learn the tools take
the time invest the time to learn the
tools I mean a good Carpenter a good
Builder we spend a lot of time to make
sure they have the I was taught in
carpentry uh the big deal my uh boss My
foreman kept drilling into me was use
the right tool you know like stop stop
there stop trying to use a chisel to
break the top of the screwdriver in a
screw you know go get a hacka CU that's
what does it right you know and and he'd
make me stop and walk over to the
toolbox and get the hat and I was trying
to ruin a chisel of it right and it it
means like bring the right tool to the
path and meditation is a tool that you
will need for every spiritual task you
will ever undertake in your life and
every other task that you'll ever
undertake in your life cuz if you can
focus and if you can concentrate you can
do everything better got it okay
all the way up to the highest levels of
T you need to be able to
concentrate think about these cool
things that are going to happen to you
if you're to meditate okay think about
them if you do then you will get to step
number one right admiration or she's
cool I I want okay got it
if you start to see how cool it is
what's going to happen if you meditate
and all the stuff I was talking about
it's going to happen you will come to a
place where you see 500 years ahead
clearly and you will come to a scope
where you are trying
to you are dealing with planets and not
people okay you are you are working with
whole worlds
okay DCI opened its
doors I don't know the first corporate
gig we ever did was a $12 billion one
okay
got
it all right your whole level will
change then you'll get syndrome then
you'll want to work hard you'll be all
excited to work hard somebody David
Swenson okay I wrote him I said when you
come teach he said he's he said guess
what I book two years ahead and I'm in
Paris what do you want me to do you know
you give me one we' notice uh but anyway
uh he he he he told me some lady came up
to him and said I want to learn yoga but
I don't want to put in all those hours
you know and he said God you're so lucky
you asked me cuz I have a yoga pill and
she said really and she said he said
yeah yeah I have a pill a pill you know
and you just take the bill once a day
and and that's it you know you don't
have to do in yoga you save all those
hours you know and she said okay give it
to me and she he gave her this bottle
you know and then uh on the side of the
bottle that says just before you take
the pill do you like these
exercises do these 30 exercises just
before you take the pill okay
anyway you got to do the work okay you
got
to so
G as I said before those four steps will
naturally trigger the other that each it
will be a
domino thing you know you like her you
want her you want her you work for her
you work for her you have fun okay it's
like the first one makes all the other
got it
okay are we
this tells me how far I have to go each
time that's
[Music]
bad yeah I we just go to 6:30 and call
okay what's the second
problem for getting me
[Music]
[Laughter]
instruction this is
experiential the second problem of
meditation is forgiving the instructions
it doesn't mean what it says okay it
doesn't mean what it says what it means
is in a in a in a in the the middle of a
meditation you lose the
object in the middle of a meditation you
lose the object you're supposed to be
meditating
about this your teacher for example but
that then suddenly you come to your
senses and you realize you've been
thinking about lunch for 10 minutes you
know like would I rather have a
cheeseburger you can't have a
cheeseburger cheese sandwich or like
that okay
okay forgetting the instructions is a
code word for losing the object of your
meditation completely and your mind your
mind's off on someone something else
okay like you you drop the object you
drop the ball okay
[Music]
right this means that your your
awareness
of your own mind has slipped and you
lost the object right if you were aware
or you were keeping the object in mind
you wouldn't lose the object if you fail
to keep it in mind you lose it got it
okay maybe he'll saying got
[Music]
it this is the
worst problem of Med meditation once
you're into the actual practice of
meditation the biggest problem for
anybody is to lose the object entirely
it's one thing not to be clear on the
object it's one thing to be holding it
Loosely or strongly but to lose it
completely is really bad okay to just
start thinking about something else is
like the worst got it got it I got it I
got
it means
and it was written by Master B
Rea
about uh300 years ago and it
[Music]
says the mind is like a wild elephant
you could say wild horse in this country
we can't really appreciate a wild
elephant but a wild horse you can
imagine right a really wild horse
uncontrollable horse
okay but they can't do as much damage as
a crazy elephant okay but anyway
longa refuses to to follow its Master's
instructions okay make Kawa chain him to
the
pillar of
chain the wild horce of the mind to the
hitching
pulse of your meditation object okay
he's comparing a pillar or a Hitching
Post or a
pole to to your meditation object and
he's comparing your mind to a wild
elephant and he's saying chain one to
the other and it's really cool when you
get good at this okay it's really cool
you sit down you say I'm going to
meditate today you say what are you
going to meditate about um um I'm going
to meditate about death about my death
which is one famous
meditation then
you in in your mind you visualize tying
your mind to that object okay it's very
beautiful
imagine my mind is here death is there I
tie my mind to death you know with my uh
sense of
awareness my my remembering the object
that the the Rope is my ability to hold
my mind on that object got it the Rope
is the ability to hold my mind on that
object and then how much slack are you
going to let it go you see it's very
beautiful idea you can let the horse go
6 feet you can let the horse go 12et but
when he hits a certain distance the r
tightens and then alarm goes off in your
mind and you say I'm losing the object
so it's a beautiful beautiful idea when
you sit down to
meditate before you do anything choose
an object of meditation that's number
one job number one job what are you
going to meditate about choose it Define
it isolate it put it in a corner of your
mind then even physically visualize
tying your mind to that and say you
ain't going away from me for more than 5
seconds before the what do you the Rope
goes
the r goes tight and then I'm pulling
you back so I've got this connection
between me and you now and until I
finish my meditation session you are
tied to me you cannot wander more than a
certain distance or I'm going to the
Rope will go talk and and I'll be aware
and I'll pull you back but it's very
beautiful you have to try it it's very
powerful tie your
mind mentally visualize tying your mind
to to that object and at the end of the
meditation on time and then you can
think about
lunch
okay in India in anci India I think it's
called a Mah what's a
[Music]
Mah El trainer driver right and uh they
have a special hook it looks like an ice
hook it's a a piece of wood and it's a
metal hook iron hook and they actually
turn the elephant by jabbing it in his
ear and ply you know and then the
elephant's like you all I guess you want
me to go to the right you know and they
train them with this very because their
elephant's skin is really thick and you
can jab it in and it doesn't really hurt
him it doesn't bleed or anything you see
and he says on the wild elephant of the
mind you will have to use your wisdom to
turn him here and there but we'll talk
about it okay
you have to tie your mind to that
object before you tie your mind to an
object you're going to have to choose an
object right so he goes off on uh an
explanation of worthy objects of
meditation
wor the objects of meditation before you
tie your mind down to an object you got
to pick an Al to and and that should be
a careful selection process don't do it
lightly right don't do it lightly
whatever object you choose will become
part of your being to the to the act of
of meditation okay so it's got to be an
amazing object don't choose your objects
lightly and when you choose them choose
something extremely powerful because
that will become part of you if your
meditation is good that will become part
of you we are constantly meditating on
the people we don't
like we spend more time in the day uh
contemplating people who have said
something bad to us people have hurt us
people have done something to us we
spend the majority of our day a great
part of our thinking time is is spent
thinking about the people who have given
us a hard time in one way or another
usually they said something to you that
you don't like or they've done something
to hurt you relationships are really
good for that and you spend a you invest
a lot of your time in in thinking how
much you dislike this person that
disliking then becomes part of your
being if you if you tie your mind to
that object you will become a dislikable
person okay and whatever object you Cho
is going to infect you so choose a good
one and not your ex spouse okay here we
go
[Music]
s this is beautiful okay this is really
beautiful I hate this
stop but you might fall over it's easier
to sit than to talk I know that I'm
sorry it's easier to talk than to sit I
experienced that in the Monastery for 20
years and they go
on and it's 100° and it's in a jungle
right
anyway he says something beautiful you
can learn to meditate on anything
anything good or bad can become a
meditation object okay you can develop
sh on any object you know like a
baseball player uh develop a good
baseball player develop sh on the ball
you know like what's the benefit of
staring at a s stitched ball I don't
know because you become like the
ball maybe that's why
anyway so the first thing to understand
is that deep states of meditation can be
developed towards any
object even even your ex spouse someone
you hate
right sh
[Music]
there was a custom in India in some
parts of India where you would close
your eyes and just try to visualize a
small stone or a small piece of wood
right you would just visualize a a stone
a pebble or you would visualize a a
little twig of wood and you would you
would just meditate on that there were
schools that did that
there was a shamanistic tradition in
tiet called B and and they would choose
a letter A as being the mother letter of
all things so they would just meditate
on
a they actually got
results they didn't stare at a stick and
they didn't stare at a rock and they
didn't draw a letter a and stare at the
a okay they did inside the
mind but there were other schools in
India and there's a thing called tra I
don't know if you've heard of it they
would actually stare at something
physically like a candle flame or or a
yantra they would draw a picture and
just stare at a picture okay he says
that's even worse than the other
two means worse
because the the ultimate object of
meditation as Master pan says in the
yoga sura at the end the last two
chapters
this meditation is something that you
develop Inside the Mind and not by
staring at something okay you it it's a
mental process it's a sharpening of the
mind focused on something within the
mind and that's what will give you
spiritual goals that's what will bring
you high spiritual goals staring at
something on the outside I I in his
system that would just be
considered useless my own experience is
that if your mind is really really
really wild elephant if your mind is
hopeless and you can't concentrate on
anything for more than a second D what
do you call
DB ad if you're like super ad maybe you
can try staring at a c i I don't know I
think it would help I do think it would
help but it's it's considered like you
know desperate measure it's better to
try to close your eyes and concentrate
okay all
right in the time of the fifth dama who
was the most famous of the Damas up till
this one who has surpassed him um he's
the one who built the Bala Palace and
things like that he unified toet as a
country
uh this particular thing really bugged
him it was a pet peeve of the fifth is
you know don't meditate staring at some
picture or something like that close
your eyes and and visualize the picture
and it's more powerful
[Music]
there was a story there's a famous story
about a guy in Ancient India and he had
trouble visualizing anything at all so
his teacher told him uh just pretend you
have horns on your head like B horns or
antlers okay and and try to meditate on
that just close your eyes and try to
feel the antlers on your head and and
try to picture them carefully
and then you know because the guy was so
bad that he couldn't do anything he
couldn't get any philosophical subject
you know he said go meditate on
horns and then his student didn't come
back and then he sent somebody to go
find out what happened and the the
student was there in the cave right and
the guy said the teacher wants to see
you and he says I can't he says what's
wrong he says every time I try to get
out the horns stick in the doorway you
know uh so
it's possible to meditate on anything
and it's possible to get good at it he
got sham he got perfect concentration it
was so perfect that he couldn't get out
the door okay it's
[Music]
possible even that kind of object you
can you can use it
okay is there a wrong talk yeah people
like you and me says right yeah I wish I
was like you okay people like you and me
he says we we have the the blessing of a
very deep instruction from the time of
the first okay from the time
[Music]
of Why not pick a meditation object
which which is sacred and already
extremely highly holy thing and use that
as your meditation object because it
will infect you it will bleed into you
you know uh choose an object which is
already extremely holy and sac and then
and then meditate on that and it will
you don't become like a baseball or
horns or a rock you become like that
Holy being that that being's blessing is
is sucked into you okay so so since the
time of the first D it was a tradition
pick a high holy object and and
visualize that as as the beginning of
your meditation practice tie your mind
to the holiest object you can imagine
and it will infect you every moment you
think about it the holiest object in a
Buddhist life is there
it's your heart teacher right so whoever
your heart teacher is everybody has a
different
one different gloves fit different
people right in your life someday in
your life you'll find your heart
DJ and then pick that you know when you
are trying to develop Focus or you're
trying to develop deep
meditation then choose as your object
the one being that you would most like
to be like right that's your heart
teacher so whoever it is whoever
everyone resonates with a different
teacher and that's
fine find your hard teacher and then
when you're trying to develop
meditation uh be with them you know put
them in front of your mind chain your
mind to them tie your mind to them have
them in your mind all day you know and
then they
will they'll affect you right you will
become like them like the person you
most love in the world meditate on that
Holy being and then and then you will
become there you will become one with
them it's very beautiful very beautiful
this is our tradition okay whoever it is
it doesn't matter okay if it's Jesus or
whatever it doesn't matter your own
teacher it doesn't matter but
um just meditate on them and then the
goal of having a teacher is to be life a
teacher and
U if you constantly medita on them then
their qualities will infect you okay
[Music]
right so means so means every moment you
think about your hard teacher you are
making new good comment just thinking
about your teacher is good comment right
it's the highest good
com dip jum means if you have certain
obstacles in your life somebody came to
me they said you know gu I've been
trying to do what you suggested about uh
in my business I've been trying to use
karmic Management in my business but I'm
having obstacles
right um the best way to remove those
obstacles is also to meditate on your
heart teacher so you get double whammy
right you get good karmic seeds every
second you meditating on them and then
the power of your teacher is
done the power of meditating on that it
removes obstacles in your life okay so
that's a that's better than a stick
right okay or a baseball
okay K that's important that's much it's
a whole different
level also later
on when we when you get to the higher
teachings and you're trying to make
contact with angels okay the the purpose
of the lower half of this of the higher
teachings is is to make contact with
holy beings right Divine beings
Angels um it'll make it a lot easier
later okay if you're meditating on some
holy
being make believe that affects the
ability to meet them for real later
[Music]
got these kinds just to spend your time
you see it's it's okay to medit about
the person at work that you don't like
and you will develop shamata towards
them you will know every fault they have
intimately years later every every
harmful thing hurtful thing they ever
said to you every they did your ex did
to you if you meditate on it you can
develop sham towards it and you will
recall every detail of every argument
you ever had with them perfectly but
what will that do to you you see what
will it do to you to tie your mind to
that object what will that do to you if
on the other hand you pick some really
holy beautiful being and you tie your
mind to them what will happen to you
what what will you become see it's very
it's very profile
[Music]
okay so then he describes the actual
meditation uh you can put your teacher
traditionally you put your teacher uh t
means uh the this high this big okay you
put a
miniature heart llama up on the top of
your head like you walk
around when you meditate especially you
can uh purposely bring that llama your
heart llama down to the level of your
naal you can meditate on them here or
you can meditate on them at your heart
or at the
at the middle of between you can
meditate on them here
okay and they mean
something they all have different uh
it's like they say uh I heard I don't
know if it's true that there's something
in a cell phone maybe the magnets in a
cell phone that if you hold it up to
your head enough it's going to affect
your head you know I heard something
like that there's some the
electromagnetic uh radiation coming out
of your phone could actually damage your
brain if you hold keep holding the phone
close to your brain okay uh it's
ring
[Music]
right so if you keep holding it up to
your ear it has some effect on your mind
right visualizing your llama here
it was vibrating so I don't really have
okay I got to be
honest putting your llama here or
putting the Llama here putting the Llama
here it affects your chakras and we'll
talk more about that maybe tomorrow okay
it affects your
chakras it's like a the cell phone thing
[Music]
then he says you see what he's getting
into and we'll just go for another 10
minutes okay CU we're already over and I
know it's hard to sit so long and that's
the nature
of that's the nature of people can only
come on
weekends
uh he's going to go through a discussion
of nice meditation objects he's going to
go through a little what do you call
shopping he's going to give you some
choices all right so uh now he says
there is a tradition where you could
people who would rather there some
people are not too good with with
visualizing pictures like they just
don't feel comfortable with it you know
like okay I don't want to visualize a
picture you know so then the Lama said
by the way there's an option with your
heart M right uh I'm not saying
visualize a photograph of them I'm
saying visualize them
there's a difference right don't
visualize a photo of them visualize them
what visualize them means that you will
feel the warmth of their body on your
body you will smell the scent of their
body in your nose you will hear their
breathing you will see their eyes blink
you see it's you're not visualizing a
photo you're visualizing a a living
being in front of you it's very powerful
you smell the scent of their body you
feel the warmth of their body you feel
their breath on your body
right that's a real visualization not
like don't visualize photos Okay uh if
you're visualizing a living thing it's
beautiful and they're blinking and then
sometimes they're smiling and sometimes
they're like
okay but but says some people will be
more
comfortable visualizing something that's
not physical then he says you could you
could focus on your mind you could
that's mahamudra right you could as a
meditation
object it's okay to select your own mind
okay you can watch your thoughts analyze
your thoughts that's an advanced
practice and I think he's about to say
[Music]
interested he said in that practice you
should refer to the works by the first
Pion Lama on what M he wrote a beautiful
beautiful text Lama Christi taught it uh
I taught it to her then she taught it to
a lot of people like think it's a very
very Exquisite teaching on meditating on
the mind okay and in a proper way in a
beneficial way so that's something you
have to he says you go check that text
okay you go get that teaching from
somebody
if you're not into
visualizing things you can work on your
own mind he gives you he's giving you
[Music]
options this is similar to other
traditions in Tibet where they are
trying
to they're trying to meditate on the
clear light or the or the nature of the
mind okay it's called the clear light or
or meeting the Mind face to face
sometimes they call it that he said this
is version of
[Music]
that those of you who have tantric
empowerment and who have tantric
training you can focus on yourself as
the daily and on yourself as the angel
right so if you have that
training a worthy meditation object is
to is to visualize your self as a Divine
being okay and that's a first level
tantric practice second level tantric
practice is
what yoga is there highest practice what
inner body okay chakr inner body they
call Rainbow body or the body that you
are working with when you do Aus okay
the body that you are working with when
you do
Asus there are certain visualizations
attached to that uh there's a
visualization of a of a of fire
Kundalini in your Naval chakra right so
that's also appropriate if you have that
instructions and if you have that
training and permission to do that it
can be a very powerful meditation object
to do Kundalini or something visualize a
dagger of fire at a certain place okay
that's also a good meditation
not few more minutes
I'm GNA do this it's I'll do it in8
minutes that'll be a record okay he
doesn't explain it and I took a long
time and I I worked it out for okay
these are Ancient Ancient meditation
objects okay they haven't been explained
properly for a few hundred
years uh uh he mentions four nice
meditation objects that were taught uh 2
and a half thousand years ago and they
got buried since then okay they got
nobody kept it teaching okay but but
it's it's there if you work at it it's
there so there are four four choices of
meditation objects okay these are four
more choices from very ancient times
from Lord Buddha himself
on meditation objects so so far we have
your rude
llama we have some inner fire we have
Angel uh we have the mind we have
different meditation objects have been
proposed why are we talking about
meditation
objects we're talking about what to tie
your mind to right why are we talking
about
that we were on the five
problems is that a
clue what's the second problem losing
the object second problem is the Rope
gets cut and you lose it the horse runs
off like that's the worst that's like
the basic number one mistake in
meditation once you get on the cushion
cuz the first problem is you don't want
to get on the cushion once you get on
the cushion the worst problem is the
horse breaks the rope and goes away
right so the reason we're talking about
potential or possible candidates for
your
meditation is that we're talking about
who you're going to tie it to to prevent
the F the second problem got it okay
here we
[Music]
go first one is called kabba kabba
means the the all-inclusive meditation
object okay the first of the four
Great subjects of meditation taught by
Lord Buddha is called the all-inclusive
object of meditation what is
that how many of the things in your life
do
something your car your wife your house
your clothing your
job your city the the roads that lead
here how many of the things in your life
do
something all of them basically
everything in your life does something
and that's why it's in your life because
you used it okay that's coverage what
did I call the first
one see that's an all-inclusive object
what do I want you to meditate on
everything in your life okay how big is
your object
now it's pretty big it's everything okay
okay got it the first meditation object
of all is called everything
okay why would you meditate on
everything if G Michael sits up there
and says nothing
works your wife doesn't work your house
doesn't work your car doesn't work your
job doesn't work going to work for money
doesn't
work starting the key on a carard
doesn't isn't what starts to
car if you get some kind of
companionship out of your spouse has
nothing to do with
them okay these are all radical things
okay the first meditation object is one
which includes everything around you and
the and the and the instruction is
realize that none of it works you can't
get anything you want out of any them
okay you want a a boy you can't do it by
going online you want to get to Phoenix
from Mesa you can't do it in a car okay
you want to make money forget working at
hours a
day okay just make the Cara make the
seat create the seat what makes the car
run is not the GS it's giving other
people
rise what makes the yoga work for you is
is nothing to do with the poses it's
it's that you have helped the sick okay
how do you find a new boyfriend go to a
nursing home and help a lonely person
you know this is how things really work
how much stuff does that cover
everything so the first meditation
object is everything got it right all
right it's cool right it's kind of cool
you can relate to that object on two
levels one is
intellectual one is oh cars don't work
people don't work companions don't work
yoga doesn't work computers don't work
food doesn't work you can relate to it
on that level you can think about it or
you can go deeper and go nonconcept Cal
you can go beyond thought on on
everything that's called meditational
emptiness
non-conceptual Beyond thinking
meditation
on all the stuff there is okay you can
relate to the first meditation object in
two ways it can be thinking or it can be
Beyond thinking right and we have to
talk about that we'll talk about that
that's the first object I almost said
got it number two number two is called
uh you can say learning okay an object
for learning I say an object for
understanding the s word
is this is where you break things down
to understand them better any object
where you are breaking things down to
understand it better is object number
two it's some kind of analytical
meditation in in tiet in in this
tradition of of the Buddha it's
considered a acceptable form of
meditation to analyze a problem or a
situation or anything let's say you have
a problem at work right you have a
problem at work your supervisor at the
person who owns the yoga studio your
workout or somebody in charge is giving
you trouble right so you meditate on
and you say why is this person giving me
TR why is this person always criticizing
me and then you think well maybe it's a
caric seed in my mind well who put the
caric seed
there I do
how I criticized other people right this
is and then you go through this train of
thought you go through this analysis you
break it down you break it down I guess
you can call number two break down
meditation Dev could be a problem
uh you break down a situation and you
analyze it into its parts and you become
a master of it oh then I should stop in
order to get my boss to stop criticizing
me I will not say anything to them I
will not confront them I will also not
not say anything to them rather I will
stop criticizing other people and I will
send that energy to my boss and that
that will fix them and then one day
they'll be praising me all right that's
how you get stuff like British Air to
happen all right it's not an accident
you design
it okay that's number two number
three uh CH up there says but
it's
[Applause]
say styles of meditation which would
improve your own behavior
yeah styles of meditation which would
improve your own
behavior for
example u a death meditation okay
you or you can say
Med um you have a problem with lust okay
you have a problem with sexual desire
like you can't control it right there's
healthy sexual desire that's fine and
and sex is fine sex is okay
good sex is good okay but to be obsessed
with it to the point where where it
makes you unhappy right where you just
like surf in the net all day and you
can't stop and you you get all nervous
and you feel disturbed by it you know
where it becomes an
obsession uh where it hurts you right
how you can take undertake meditations
that would fix that or you have an
alcoholism problem it's addiction right
any kind of addiction problem you could
undertake a meditation that would fix
that what would be such a meditation um
in the case of sexual desire it could be
meditating the traditional one is
meditating on death you know you you
open up a Playboy magazine or you go on
the web and you look at the lady's body
and you try to imagine how it's going to
be three weeks after she dies in the
coffin with the maggots crawling out of
the nose and out of the anus and out of
the sexual organ
and then suddenly your desire
goes all right these are called
corrective meditation objects so you can
undertake what if you're just not a nice
person you can do a tum L right you
could do uh meditations where you take
away other people's pain or you give
them happiness right and this would make
you a less selfish person so these are
corrective meditation objects right
meditating on offering another
person the things they want in their
life on your breath as a meditation is
number is the third type of meditation
object
corrective it makes you a Kinder softer
person right number four and then we'll
start
[Music]
styles of meditation which are meant to
uh
affect your generally uh your general
negative emotions okay it's similar to
number three but it's different number
three was corrective meditations for
specific problems you have number four
is also corrective meditation still a
num in those of you who not to B and
it's still a Nong Nong distributes to
both andong although they don't say it
in the text
uh you can correct your negative
emotions there are two
methods one is called sh number 10 it
means
uh go more and more deep go more and
more subtle right going more and more
subtle is the number one version of
number four okay I almost say got
it
going finer and finer in your what does
that mean you sit down you start
meditating all you can think about is
the cars outside you hear the car there
was a motorcycle this morning right did
you hear there was a motorcycle with a
glass pack on it and uh okay so that you
say okay I'm not going to listen to
motorcycles anymore and you bring your
meditation it's a what do you call a
narrowing of your meditation range so
you start with listening to the
glasspack muffler on the motorcycle
outside then you say I'm I'm not going
to listen to that I'm bringing my mind
closer you start to concentrate
on the air conditioner turning on and
off in the room this morning all right
so at least you got your mind out of the
into the
church Ken L Christine and I went to Ken
we said we bowed to him we said okay
we've come to ask you for advice for the
threee
retreat and and we had scheduled 3 or 4
hours and he said he leaned over and he
said keep your mind in the earth
goodbye that was
it so it's
narrowing okay you start with the street
you start with Southern Avenue and then
you narrow it to the church and the air
conditioner and then you say I'm not
going to listen to the church noises
anymore and you start to listening to
the sniffling and coughing of the people
in the room right and you say I'm not
going to listen to that anymore and you
narrow it down to people shuffling
around and then you say I'm not going to
listen to the shuffling around anymore
and then you start to go to your own
breath and you you watch your own breath
which is kind of noisy relatively noisy
then you say I'm just going to listen to
my nose hairs
move which you can get to all right you
will I'm going to listen to my nose
hairs move then you say I'm going finer
I will go into the my inner ear and
listen to the blood flow in my inner ear
I will concentrate on the blood flowing
through my inner ear and you can you can
listen to that then you can say oh I'm
going to listen to I'm going to go
deeper than that I'm going to listen I'm
going to follow The Prana moving through
my body okay I'm just going to put my
mind on the pr flowing to my body and
then you say I'm going to put my mind on
one of my chakras and then I'm going to
put my mind on a point inside one of my
chakras which is equal to a great
sand I'm going to keep my mind in an
area of my heart chakra Naval chakr is
safer which is as big as a grain of sand
and keep it there what's
happening touches see you are you are
narrowing narro and Nar it's called sh
number 10 means going from the more
gross to the more subtle from gross to
sub gross to subtle the the noise inside
your ear becomes gross
on the next in the next hour you see at
5:00 the noise inside your ear is subtle
at 4:00 you've gone to the PIRA and that
is gross and you keep going more and
more subtle dropping levels dropping
levels drop drop drop drop
drob and then that helps you overcome
your negative emotions your desire for
food your desire for fame more attention
my my favorite one and or that kind of
thing all right you
naturally as your mind gets
more subtle your desire for those things
will will lessen it is not a permanent
fix it is not a permanent fix you get up
you get out of meditation you get in
your car you drive the noise of the
glass pack becomes
subtle and you're worrying about Highway
60 you're worrying about 12 cars on
harway 60 around you you could care less
about a single motorcycle see everything
can be subtle everything can be rough
it's not a safe meditation it's done by
a lot of westerners they think if I
could just get
quiet I'm I'm meditating it's okay it's
a temporary fix when you get up and you
get in your car it's all going to melt
you won't remember the blood in your
ears anymore because you'll be trying to
survive on Highway
60 the second part of number four is the
ultimate fix what's that and then if
somebody tells me you can go home
yeah emptiness go to emptiness right go
to The Emptiness of that
object instead of trying to feel calm
about the car that's not working very
well understand that you can fix it by
giving other people's
rights understand go to the real fix
it's stop pulling around with trying to
feel better about a car that doesn't
work because that's the number one step
of the
last stop trying to feel good about a
car that doesn't work right stop trying
to feel calm about a car that doesn't
work right and scary and it's it's
making bad noises and it might kill you
on the next trip to Camp ver you see
stop stop relating to it that way stop
trying to be calm about bad stuff rather
change the kic states which are creating
it in the first place and that's the
ultimate form of meditation that's the
final for that's the final meditation
update I want my car to work better so
I'm going to give rides to anyone I see
who needs one because that's what makes
my car work better did you didn't you
ever wonder why you pay a lot of money
and you get a car and it
sucks and then you buy an old slab with
a broken window that doesn't even roll
right and it goes forever uh I went
online to uh find out how to fix the
headlight on a 1980 vcal stationary
I had to wait through all this stuff
there was an article there was a Wiki
Answers thing and some 15-year-old kid
was riding in and he said Can someone
tell me how to destroy a 1980 Bal
station wagon cuz my parents made me
take it and it won't stop you know it
won't break down and I want a decent car
and does anybody have suggestions and
then all these people wrote in and they
said pour sugar in the gas tank and pour
water in the oil and it was a whole nice
list of just how to destroy a 1980
B so the real fix for a bad car you see
some people spend a lot of money and get
a bad car right a lemon and then some
people don't spend any money and they
get stuck with a 1980 vble that refuses
to die uh understand that it's all Karma
and it's all comes from giving other
people ride so need ride right and
meditate on that and that's the final
object we have
completed uh the four most ancient
meditation objects suggested by Lord
Buddha and nobody explains them you
won't see an explanation there he just
makes a list they've been listing the
four of them for hundreds of years and
everybody forgot what they
were uh so now you you have that
teaching all right
[Music]
okay we'll break and we'll come back at
eight have a nice uh take some good rest
okay if you're interested and you're
bored you can go to Paradise Cafe and
other people will be there and you can
do this afternoon's homework together
with them while you eat dinner all
right maybe
[Music]
body
okay have a nice